Guide to the William Drenttel Collection of Imre Reiner
Yale University Arts Library
William Drenttel Collection of Imre Reiner
1946-2006
AOB 45
Yale University Arts Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists of articles and examples of Imre Reiner's designs and a small amount of correspondence collected by graphic designer William Drenttel.
Drenttel, William, 1953-2013
Reiner, Imre, 1900-1987
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Drenttel, 2006 & 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Imre Reiner, a respected graphic designer, type designer and illustrator, was born in 1900 in Yugoslavia. At an early age his family moved to Romania. At age 15, during World War I, he left home to live independently and attend school for sculpture first in Romania, then in Hungary. In 1920 he moved to Germany, and changed his focus to the graphic arts. In the early 1920s, he traveled frequently in Europe and also visited Chicago and New York. In the late 1920s he started to design typefaces. He became an advisor to the Monotype Corporation in the mid 1930s and made frequent trips to London. In the 1940s he illustrated many books, including editions of Goethe, Rilke, Voltaire and Dickens. In 1950 he became a citizen of Switzerland. Exhibitions of his work were frequent in the late 1940s and early 1950s at such places as the Musée Royal des Beaux-Arts in Antwerp and Museu de Arte in Sao Paolo, as well as at several galleries in the United States. Reiner continued to publish books, illustrate, and have exhibitions internationally until his death in 1987. His typefaces include: Gotika, Symphonia, Matura, Figaro, Reiner Script, Mustang, Bazaar, and London Script.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of articles and examples of Imre Reiner's designs and a small amount of correspondence collected by graphic designer William Drenttel.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Art work and designs, 1946-1959. II. Articles, 1946-1975. III. Materials related to Reiner, 1963-1985. IV. Correspondence, 1946-1948, 1998.
Graphic design (Typography); Reiner, Imre, 1900-1987
- Art work and designs, 1946-1959; Series I
  - Bauer Beton, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Celestial Omnibus." Dimensions, Volume 3: Number 1., Spring 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Die Nacht, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Publication also includes photograph [of 1946 Reiner sketch?], inscribed by Reiner and laid in.
  - Graphis, Volume 8: Number 40., January 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Graphis, Volume 16: Number 89., May / June 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Print: A Quarterly Journal of the Graphic Arts, Volume V: Number 4., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reiner Script [type specimen]., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Signature: A Quadrimestrial of Typography and Graphic Arts, New Series: 14., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Symphonie: Nach Entwurfen von Imre Reiner., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Three 'Monotype' Scripts by Imre Reiner: Matura, Mercurius and Pepita., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Typographica 2: Contemporary Typography and Graphic Art [photocopy of cover]., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Articles, 1946-1975; Series II
  - By Imre Reiner
    - "Visual Qualities of Corvinus and Symphony." Print: A Quarterly Journal of the Graphic Arts, Volume VI: Number 1., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11a)
  - About Imre Reiner
    - "Imre Reiner." Graphis, Volume 2: Number 13., January / February 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Imre Reiner: Skriftkunstner, Typografiker, Forfatter, Maler og grafiker., August 18, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Imre Reiner: Vier Gemalde und funf Zeichnungen." du: Kulturelle Monatsschrift, Jahrg. 22: Number 253., March 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Materials related to Reiner, 1963-1985; Series III
  - Below the Fold, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Book Typography, 1815-1965: Index page [photocopy]., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Corvinus" Type materials [photocopies]., undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Künstler Lexikon der Schweiz: XX. Jahrundert [photocopy of Reiner entry]., 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous [photocopies]., 1975 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Reiner titles: Card catalog cards [photocopies], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Thames and Hudson Manual of Typography: Index page [photocopy]., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1946-1948 1998; Series IV
  - Autograph material: Including letters to George Wittenborn, postcard, entry forms for AIGA exhibition, publisher's promotions for books illustrated by Reiner, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence and Imre book listings from Andras Furesz, April 28-June 14, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)